Eddie Cochran Historical Organization Collection ARC.0005
Library and Archives
Eddie Cochran Historical Organization Collection
1950-1993 and undated
ARC.0005
Library and Archives
4.34 Linear feet 3 records cartons and 1 flat box
The Eddie Cochran Historical Organization spans the years 1950-1993. The collection provides rich documentation of Eddie Cochran’s career, focusing on his vast impact on early rock and rockabilly music. Other artists included in the collection are Gene Vincent and Sharon Sheeley. The documents also provide insight into the workings of the Eddie Cochran Historical Organization, showcasing Cochran’s impact on individuals. The collection provides a unique look into the enthusiastic lengths music fans will go to in order to locate information about their idols and to preserve and honor their legacies. The collection is comprised of the administrative files of the historical organization; graphic materials depicting images of Cochran, including photographs, posters, and postcards; printed materials featuring information about Cochran, including newspapers, books, booklets, periodicals, clippings, and sheet music; and audiovisual materials featuring recordings by Cochran, in the form of videotapes, 45 RPM records, LP records, and mini-discs.
Eddie Cochran Historical Organization
Biography and Historical Note
Biography of Eddie Cochran
1938 October 3 Born in Albert Lea, Minn.
1954 Began his musical career in California
1956 Cut first record and signed with Liberty Records
1958 Recorded his biggest hits “Summertime Blues” and “C’mon Everybody”
1960 April 17 Died in a traffic accident in Somerset (England)
1987 Inducted into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame
Though Eddie Cochran was only twenty-one when he died, he left his mark as a rock and roll pioneer. He epitomized the sound and style of the Fifties rebel rocker and was an innovative and highly influential guitarist. He was also proficient on piano, bass and drums. His short career, spanning only 6 years, produced many hit singles including “Summertime Blues,” “C’mon Everybody,” “Twenty Flight Rock,” “Something Else,” and “Nervous Breakdown.” These singles inspired many major artists; the first song Paul McCartney and John Lennon ever played together was “Twenty Flight Rock.” Other artists that have covered his songs include The Who, the Sex Pistols, Jimi Hendrix and The Clash.
Eddie Cochran only released one album during his lifetime, which was tragically cut short when he was killed in a traffic accident while riding in a taxi on his way to a London airport at the end of a British tour. Artist Gene Vincent and songwriter Sharon Sheeley, who was Cochran’s fiancé, were also injured in the accident. In his death, Cochran achieved iconic status with many generations of rock and rollers and his legacy and influence can still be seen today.
Historical Note: Bruce C. Blake and the Eddie Cochran Historical Organization
1990 Summer First meeting of organization
1991 Incorporated as a Minnesota non-profit organization
1991 June 21-23 Held first annual Eddie Cochran weekend in Alberta Lea, Minn.
Bruce C. Blake founded the Eddie Cochran Collection in 1990 in Cochran’s hometown of Alberta Lea, Minnesota. A bill collector by trade, Blake was 26 years old when he formed the organization with the objective of honoring Eddie Cochran and promoting his music in the Alberta Lea area. Most local people were unaware that Cochran was from Alberta Lea before this organization was formed. Cochran’s family has since moved and he normally stated he was from Oklahoma (where his parents were from) to improve his country music credibility. The idea for the organization’s name, ECHO, was based on the name, EKKO, an early recoding label on which Cochran appeared. The original members of the organization included local individuals, several of which grew up in the area Cochran lived, those who liked early rock and roll music, and those acquainted with Cochran and believed it should be a source of pride for the community. The organization achieved its goals and created a strong memory of Cochran in his hometown and preserving his legacy for future generation. The organization disbanded in the late 1990s.
For further information on Bruce Blake and the Eddie Cochran Historical Organization, contact the Freeborn County Historical Museum.
Sources
Bream, Jon. “Hometown, Home State Finally Pay Tribute to Eddie Cochran.” Minneapolis-St. Paul Star Tribune. June 13, 1991.
Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum. “Eddie Cochran Biography.” http://rockhall.com/inductees.
Provenance
The Bruce C. Blake Collection of the Eddie Cochran Historical Organization was received by the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame Foundation, Inc. as two gifts from Bruce C. Blake: the first on June 21, 1993 and, the second, June 21, 1994.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Patrons must sign the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibility and Privacy Rights form before using this collection. Please contact reference staff before visiting the Library and Archives to use this collection.
Blake, Bruce C.; Cochran, Eddie, 1938-1960; Sheeley, Sharon, 1940-2002; Vincent, Gene, 1935-1971; 45 RPM records.; Books.; Fan clubs.; Files (Records).; Guitar music (Rock); Music appreciation.; Music fans.; Newspapers.; Pamphlets.; Periodicals.; Photographs.; Postcards.; Rock music.; Rockabilly music.; Rockabilly musicians.; Sheet music.; Traffic fatalities.; Video tapes.; Vinyl discs.
- Series I: Administrative Files, 1957-1993 and undated
  Scope and Contents
  Contains files and documents dealing with the administrative aspects of the Eddie Cochran Historical Organization as well as the original Eddie Cochran Fan Club. Some documents include correspondence, newsletters, membership information and business cards. This series is arranged by type and then chronologically within the groupings.
  - Original correspondence between fan club president and a member, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Various correspondences from Tony Freer looking for information about Cochran, 1980-1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Fan letters written to Cochran, copies and originals (14 letters), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Original fan club lists of members, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fan club stationary and envelopes (3 copies of each), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Original sheets “To Start a Fan Club” from Cochran fan club, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Original page from DIG magazine with article “How to form a Fan Club”, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - ½ sheets sent out to those wishing to start a fan club (3 copies), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Original questionnaire from fan club, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - List of Eddie Cochran’s favorite things, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Original “Price List” of materials from fan club, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Memorial sheets (3 copies), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Memorial sheets (3 copies), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Membership flyers (8 copies), undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Fan club membership cards in pink, green, yellow, blue and white (3 copies of each), undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Original Eddie Cochran business cards with Liberty Records (2 cards), undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Original “Melodie Boys” business card (2 cards), undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - SGT. Jan S. Olson business cards (7 copies), undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Original copies of the Eddie Cochran Fan Club newsletter, volume two, 1963 October (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Rock de Lux, 1985, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - RVTA 66, number 22, 1987 October (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - RVTA 66, number 66, 1991 October (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Outlaw Rockin’ newsletters, volumes 5, 11, 14-22, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Gene Vincent and Eddie Cochran International Fan Club magazine, GIT IT, issues 1 through 8, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Cochran Connection Newsletter, volume 1, issue 2 (3 copies), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cochran Connection Newsletter, volume 1, issue 3 (3 copies), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Cochran Connection Newsletter, volume 2, issue 1 (3 copies), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - “Summertime Blues” Spanish fan club newsletter, volumes 1 through 8, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Papers from the Eddie Cochran Memorial Society, 1966-1973 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Clipping from the Eddie Cochran Memorial Fund, 1968-1991 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Cochran poster from Hydra Records, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Color photocopy of watercolor of Cochran done by a French fan, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Cochran article on photographic paper, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - “The Girl Can’t Help It” promotional picture, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Eddie Cochran discography, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Eddie Cochran biography, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Interview transcript, Dick D’Agostin and the Swingers (2 copies), undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - “Be-Bop-A-Lula” production information, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Maps and information about area Cochran died, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Original calendar from New Musical Express, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - “Boy Meets Girl” original song sheet, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Sharon Sheeley song lyrics, 1962 October 9 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Series II: Graphic Materials, 1950-1993 and undated
  Divided into 3 subseries: photographic materials, postcards and posters. Each subseries contain graphic materials featuring images of Eddie Cochran. The subseries are arranged by size and then chronologically within each grouping.
  - Subseries 1: Photographic Materials
    - 8x10 color photograph of “Go, Johnny, Go” artwork for the movie, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 8x10 color photographs of Cochran from “The Girl Can’t Help It” (2 photographs), undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Signed 8x10 promotional photograph of Cochran, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Signed 8x10 photographs of Bobby Cochran (5 copies), undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 8x10 photograph of Cochran with his confirmation class, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 8x10 photograph of Cochran with DJ Freeman Hover in Denver (6 copies), 1957 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 8x10 photograph of Cochran from “Go, Johnny, Go”, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 8x10 photographs of Cochran taken on his 21st birthday (6 photographs), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 8x10 photograph of Eddie Cochran signed by Alice Cochran, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 8x10 photographs of Cochran leaning against a tree (5 copies), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 8x10 promotional photograph of Cochran (4 copies), undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 8x10 photograph of Cochran and Sharon Sheeley in 4 different poses, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 8x10 promotional photograph of Cochran, facial close-ups (13 copies), undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 8x10 photograph of Cochran looking over his shoulder (27 copies), undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 8x10 photograph of Cochran, in jacket, with hands resting on back of chair (25 copies), undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 8x10 promotional photograph of Cochran with the Flamingos, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 8x10 photograph of Cochran’s grave, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 8x10 photographs of the Cochran Brothers, (2 photographs), undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 8x10 photograph of Cochran with fans, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 8x10 photograph of Cochran with Gene Vincent, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - 8x10 photograph of Cochran playing for 5 people, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - 8x10 photograph of Cochran at Goldstar studios with backing band (2 photographs), undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - 8x10 photograph of Cochran (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - 8x10 photographs of Cochran with and without various musicians (29 photographs), undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - 8x10 original photograph of Cochran from the Legendary Masters series, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - 8x10 photographs of Cochran from “Untamed Youth” (2 photographs), undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - 8x8 photograph of Cochran with 2 fans, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - 8x8 Color photographs of Cochran in and out of a hammock (12 photographs), undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - 8x8 sepia-colored insert form the Legendary Masters series, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - 5x7 photographs of Cochran from childhood (40 photographs), undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - 5x7 photographs of Cochran (19 copies), undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - School snapshots of Cochran (2 copies), 1953 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Color snapshot of Cochran, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Various snapshots of Cochran (6 photographs), undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Various wallet sized snapshots of Cochran (44 photographs), undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Snapshots of Cochran from “The Girl Can’t Help It” (4 photographs), undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Reproduced snapshots of Cochran (18 photographs), undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Promotional snapshots (4 photographs), undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Snapshot photographs taken in London near the area Cochran died (49 photographs), undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Photograph negatives (3 copies), undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Subseries 2: Postcards
    - Postcards of Cochran (9 copies), undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Subseries 3: Posters
    - Eddie Cochran and Gene Vincent promotional color concert poster, Saturday February 13 (Box 3, Object 1)
    - Eddie Cochran promotional black and white poster, Liberty Records: C’Mon Everybody, undated (Box 3, Object 2)
    - Eddie Cochran promotional black and white poster, Liberty Records: Hallelujah, I Love Her so, undated (Box 3, Object 3)
    - Eddie Cochran promotional black and white poster, Liberty Records: Sittin’ in the Balcony/Dark and Lonely Street and We Can’t Sing Rhythm and Blues/Dreamer’s Bay, undated (Box 3, Object 4)
- Series III: Printed Materials, 1953-1993 and undated
  Divided into 6 subseries: newspapers, books, booklets, periodicals, clippings and sheet music. Each subseries contain materials relating to Eddie Cochran’s life, career, death and legacy. The files are arranged alphabetically by title and/or author and then chronologically.
  - Subseries 1: Newspapers
    - Chadron Record, 1959 April 2 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - City Pages (3 copies), 1991 May 8 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Daily Mirror, 1992 January (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Mid-Coast Music (3 copies), 1991 May (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - St. Pioneer Press, 1991 June 22 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - St. Paul Pioneer Press (3 copies), 1993 April 17 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Star Tribune, 1991 June 2 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Sunday Globe, 1992 October 4 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Twin Cities Reader, 1991 June 19 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 2: Books
    Separated Materials
    Books have been transfered to the library collection. Please search for "Bruce C. Blake Collection of the Eddie Cochran Historical Organization" in the library catalog for a list of donated titles.
  - Subseries 3: Booklets
    - Album of Hillbilly and Western Favorites souvenir booklet, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Biggest Show of the Stars for ‘57 tour booklet, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Country and Western Caravan on Tour souvenir booklet, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Discography: Gene Vincent, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Fan Club Directory, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Rock and Roll Scene booklet, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Something Else: A Tribute to Eddie Cochran booklet, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 4: Periodicals
    - Guitar Player, 1983 December (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Musician Magazine, 1991 November (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Not Fade Away, 1977-1979 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Now Dig This, Issues 61,68,85, 1988-1990 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Photoplay, 1960 August (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Record Collector, 1986 March (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Record Collector, 1992 June (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - TV Guide, 1992 November 7 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Subseries 5: Clippings
    - Newspaper clippings on Eddie Cochran, 1959-1993 (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
  - Subseries 6: Sheet Music
    - 19 songs (photocopies), 1959, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - “Drive in Show”, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - “Summertime Blues” (3 copies), 1958 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - “This Should Go on Forever”, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Series IV: Audiovisual Materials, 1957-1988 and undated
  Divided into 4 subseries: videotapes, 45 RPM records, LP records and mini-discs. Each subseries contain materials recorded by or relating to Eddie Cochran. The items are arranged alphabetically within each subseries.
  - Subseries 1: Videotapes
    - Bobby Cochran and the Rhythm Rockers, undated (Box 4, Object 21)
    - Bobby Cochran and the Rock Around the Clock Show, undated (Box 4, Object 22)
    - “Go, Johnny, Go”, 1985 (Box 4, Object 23)
    - “Tear it Up: The Rockabilly Documentary”, undated (Box 4, Object 24)
  - Subseries 2: 45 RPM Records
    45 RPM records have been transfered to the library collection. Please search for "Bruce C. Blake Collection of the Eddie Cochran Historical Organization" in the library catalog for a list of donated titles.
  - Subseries 3: LP Records
    LP Records have been transfered to the library collection. Please search for "Bruce C. Blake Collection of the Eddie Cochran Historical Organization" in the library catalog for a list of donated titles.
  - Subseries 4: Mini-Discs
    - Eddie Cochran. Lil’ Bit of Gold. Undated by Rhino Records. R3-73005. Compact Disc. (2 copies) (Box 4, Object 25)